(suspenseful music)
- [Narrator] It is August 5, 2010
at the San Jose Gold and
Copper Mine in Chile,
and more than 2,000
feet below the surface,
a couple of miners notice
a faint rumbling sound
echoing through the rocks.
(ground rumbling)
The miners have heard
rumblings like this before
as the rock adjusts to new excavations,
but today these rumblings are
much more frequent than usual.
(clock ticking)
The time is 2:00 PM,
and the workers are trying
to wrap up as much work
as possible before they will
be picked up by a work truck,
which will drive them all the
way to the surface for lunch.
(suspenseful music fades out)
But then, suddenly, they
hear something much louder
than the previous rumblings.
(ground rumbling loudly)
(intense music)
The blast sends those
working on the higher levels
of the mine to the ground
and causes the tunnels
and shafts to collapse.
(rocks clacking)
Large rocks tumble down,
sweeping across the workers,
and all they can do is hang
onto them and ride out.
(rocks clacking)
The workers have no way of knowing yet,
but the San Jose mine has just collapsed,
trapping them beneath the surface.
(intense music continues)
The mine is located in the Atacama Desert,
one of the driest areas in the world.
Conditions here are so extreme
that the site is often used
for simulations of Mars expeditions,
and yet, the Atacama Desert
is an incredibly valuable asset to Chile
and that is because of what lies beneath:
abundant mineral resources
from copper to silver to gold.
When looking at the
mine from above ground,
its true scale is hidden.
To go in, there's an unassuming
five by five meter entrance,
and it leads to a tunnel,
known as the ramp,
that spirals downwards
with several branching paths
leading off into the mountain,
the workers orient themselves underground
based on a level system using
sea level for reference.
The entrance is at level 720,
which is 720 meters above sea.
(intense music continues)
When the mine collapsed,
some of the workers were
as deep as level 40.
(truck engine rumbling)
In the immediate
aftermath of the collapse,
some of the workers tried to
make a break for the surface.
They get into a truck
and drive up the ramp.
However, they quickly get stuck,
as the road is so littered with debris
that they need to continue on foot.
They reach level 190
where they find the cause of the collapse:
a giant slab of diorite
estimated as tall as a 45-story building
and weighing 770,000 tons
has broken off from the mountain
and crashed down the mine
completely blocking the ramp.
The workers are trapped,
and their only option now
is to retreat back down.
Located at level 90,
there is a small enclosed
space known as The Refuge.
It is designated as an
emergency shelter area
for situations like this.
Fresh air is pumped in from the surface
and emergency food and medicine
is locked in metal cabinets
that are to be opened
should the need arise.
(intense music continues)
As the workers descend
back down into the mine,
the word spreads of the collapse
until the news eventually
reaches the shift supervisor,
Luis Urzua, who is working at level 90.
He orders the workers to
take shelter in The Refuge
and heads down further into the mine
to evacuate those working below.
Because of the distance from the collapse
and ear protection worn by the men,
those down below didn't
realize what was happening
until Urzua orders them to The Refuge.
Once everyone has gathered together,
Urzua then conducts a roll call
and counts 33 man trapped.
With the ramp completely closed,
some of the workers realized
that they might be able
to escape through the ventilation shafts
that lead to various parts of the mine.
According to standard safety regulations,
there should be ladders that can be used
to climb through those shafts.
To investigate this, a
small group breaks off,
but when they get there, they
discover a heartbreaking site.
(suspenseful music)
There's no ladder in the shaft.
The owners of the mine never
finished installing them.
Back at the surface,
the dust cloud has begun
pouring out of the entrance.
As the supervisors realize
that something must have
gone terribly wrong,
one man, who at the time of the collapse
was driving up the ramp,
is able to make it out through
the blinding ash of dust.
With the supervisors present,
one would expect immediate
help would be organized.
However, they decide that
there is nothing they can do
until the dust fully settles.
(suspenseful music continues)
Hours pass until they begin
their descent down the ramp
where they encountered the blockage.
Standing face to face with the enormity
of the diorite block
completely obstructing the ramp,
the supervisors realize that
there is no coming through,
and still, precious time
is lost in the next steps.
Despite having a phone line at the mine
for emergencies such as this,
the mine's owners decide
to instead head back
towards the closest town
in order to get cell
service to call for help.
Finally, after more than
five hours since the collapse
authorities are called.
The news gets passed from
the local fire department
and onward until it eventually reaches
the Disaster Office of Chile's
Ministry of the Interior.
(intense music)
The government deployed
special forces in climbing gear
with the hope that they could
free the trapped miners.
The idea is the same one
that the miners had in
the immediate aftermath:
using the ventilation
shafts as an escape route.
As these forces climb down
the shafts, secured to ropes,
they are alarmed to see cracks
in the walls of the shaft,
a result of the diorite block
pushing against the walls
and squeezing the shaft.
(intense music continues)
Despite the danger of another collapse,
the rescuers continue on
determined to reach any man trapped below.
They're able to make it to level 268
before they face a pile of rock and debris
that looks as if it
could fall on top of them
at any moment.
These shafts are way too unstable
and as they begin to retreat back,
suddenly the rocks begin
to fall around them
proving that their worries are justified.
The rescuers manage to make it
out of the ventilation shafts
and back to safety,
but now they need to report
to those waiting anxiously on the surface
that a rescue like this
will be impossible.
The only option left will be to drill.
(suspenseful music)
2,300 feet beneath the rescuers
delivering the bad news
the workers who returned
from their own failed attempt
at navigating the ventilation shafts
must also return to The Refuge
with bad news of their own.
As experienced miners,
many realized that this is
going to take days if not weeks.
The enormity of what has happened
hits some harder than others,
and it particularly affects
Shift Supervisor Urzua.
Urzua makes an announcement
that, beginning with this moment,
he's no longer the boss,
and that they will need to
treat each other as equals.
Knowing they're going
to be trapped for long,
the miners next take inventory
of the supplies in The Refuge,
and the workers are soon
met with another heartbreak.
What was supposed to be enough food
to feed an entire shift
of workers for two days
turned out to be one can of salmon,
one can of peaches, one can
of peas, 18 cans of tuna,
93 packages of cookies,
24 liters of condensed
milk, eight of them expired,
10 bottles of water, and
some medicine, also expired.
All of this will need to
be shared among 33 men
and has to last potentially for weeks.
(somber music)
Looking at the meager food reserves,
the men come up with a plan
to make it last as long as possible.
Every miner will get one meal a day
consisting of one cookie
and one spoonful of tuna
mixed with water that has been heated
to turn it into a broth.
It is a meal that has
less than 300 calories,
but it is all they can do.
Drinking water, fortunately,
is less of an issue.
Even though they only have 10 bottles
of clean, fresh water,
there are large tanks nearby
filled with thousands of
liters of industrial water
that is used to keep the engines
of their machines cool.
This water is drinkable,
even though it isn't exactly desirable,
as it is contaminated with oil.
With a somewhat stable plan
for food and water set,
a new constant threat
begins to materialize:
mental collapse.
(somber music)
Would anyone even be searching for them
or would they just be presumed dead
and the mine be sealed off?
To keep these shadows at bay,
one of the workers, an electrician,
figures out a way to keep
their flashlights charged.
He does so by wiring them
up to the large batteries
of the work vehicles,
and the miners even decide
to use the artificial light
to simulate night and day,
keeping track of time
and maintaining a comforting
sleep rhythm for themselves.
But the light isn't enough
to fend off the shadows of the mind,
and so the pastor decides to step in.
Jose Henriquez isn't
actually a pastor by trade,
but he is a devout evangelical man.
The workers soon call him Pastor,
a nickname that he earns
because he leads the men in prayer.
These prayer sessions become
a fixture in the men's cycle.
Have a restless sleep throughout the night
plagued by nightmares,
wake up to the artificial sun
that is their flashlights,
join together for a sermon
delivered by Pastor Henriquez,
and then eat a single meal of one cookie
and broth made from oily water,
and most of all, simply wait,
never knowing if anyone
is even bothering to search for them.
(intense music)
Though completely separated
from the society above,
the miners created their own
functioning society underground
from pastor, to doctor,
and, although he had
formally stepped down,
Urzua still was seen by
many as some form of leader.
You could think of it
as a city below ground
and just like there was a city below,
above ground, a new city
also started forming.
Many of the miner's
families were frustrated
by the lack of communication,
and news reports offered confusing
and conflicting information.
Therefore, many wives, and parents,
and children decided to
head to the mine directly.
(intense music)
One of the miner's sisters, Maria Segovia,
immediately begins to take charge
on behalf of other family members
in demanding to know
what is going to be done
to rescue the miners.
She declares that the families
will camp outside of the mine
until their loved ones
are returned to them,
and others follow her.
(intense music continues)
Tents are brought out,
and the families begin
to sleep every night at the site.
And every day, Segovia once again, demands
to know what is happening
until she and the other
family members are pushed back
and a perimeter is set
up around the rescue site
with only authorized
personal allowed to enter.
(spoon clacking)
Not to be deterred,
Segovia leads efforts
to get more information
by banging pots and pans
at the edge of the perimeter...
(intense music)
(clacking continues)
Until an official comes over
to let them know the progress.
(intense music continues)
And with every passing day,
the tents continue to grow
into essentially a new city,
and its residents decide
to give it a name:
Camp Hope.
(intense music continues)
Meanwhile, Segovia also
earns herself a nickname:
La Alcaldesa, The Mayor of Camp Hope.
(intense music fades out)
(intense music)
Without knowing about the
formation of Camp Hope above them,
by the time the fourth day
underground comes about,
the workers are increasingly worried,
that is until someone hears a
faint sound in the distance.
Everyone quiets, and they listen together,
scarcely able to believe it.
(drill rattling)
It is the sound of a drill
traveling through the mountain.
(drill rattling)
Up above, a rotary drill
has started its work
creating a borehole down to
an area close to The Refuge
where rescuers correctly
believe the workers to be.
But there are some issues.
The simplest method would be
to drill straight down to their target.
However, this would mean setting
up the massive drilling rig
right above the cavity left behind
by the giant diorite block
that has broken off,
and, because of that cavity,
the ground is too unstable here.
Therefore, the drill has to be set up
at a different location,
and the hole will need to
be dug at a 78 degree angle.
Their target is a small area 32 feet wide,
and they will need to travel
through over 2,000 feet
of diorite to reach it.
If the drill deviates
just by a small amount,
by the time they reached the target,
they could be completely off.
It is at this point during the rescue
that yet another person
joins the operation.
Andre Sougarret works as an
administrator and engineer
for the El Teniente Mine in Chile.
This mine is significantly
larger than the San Jose mine,
and rescues are much more common there,
which makes Sougarret an
expert in these situations.
(intense music)
Once he arrives, Sougarret
immediately gets to work,
taking over and scaling
up the rescue operation.
He deploys eight additional drills,
all of them to run concurrently,
each making its own borehole
with the same target near The Refuge.
He knows they need to work fast,
and the more opportunities they have
to hit the target, the better.
(intense music continues)
While the drills continue,
Sougarret decides to
simultaneously revisit the idea
of using the ventilation shafts.
He sends climbers back into the mine
with the goal to clear these shafts,
and as the rescuers get
to work on this plan,
they soon make a scary observation.
They realize that the diorite block
is actually still moving,
slowly sinking lower
and lower into the mine.
It could completely
collapse at any moment,
and a difficult decision is made.
The entrance of the San
Jose mine needs to be closed
and sealed off permanently,
and they will need to
put all of their hopes
into the drills.
(suspenseful music)
And as if closing the mine
wasn't bad news enough,
the drilling is not
going according to plan.
After three days of digging,
one of the drills is bending
in the wrong direction.
With no way to fix it,
this hole will need to be given up on
and restarted at a different location.
And it's seeming more and
more likely to rescuers
that the workers down below
would surely have perished by this point.
The drills continue on
with few believing they
will reach anything
when suddenly the unthinkable happens.
The drill has broken into
a cavern in the mine,
the loud drilling is stopped,
and the rescuers think
that they can hear a
tapping sound on the drill.
(metal clanking)
Scarcely able to believe it,
they quickly bring up the drill
in order to lower a camera instead.
And once that is lowered,
they turn the camera around the cavern,
capturing the walls,
but unfortunately they
see nothing but emptiness.
(somber music)
With sunken hearts,
they raise their camera back up.
The tapping sound could
have been anything,
and they go back to drilling.
Down below, in The Refuge, the
workers are in a rough shape.
It has been over two weeks
since they've been trapped,
and, in order to survive longer,
they now only eat every second day.
They can see the weight
loss on each other,
and, with now noticeably less energy,
it is harder to keep moving.
Some of the workers even venture down
lower into the depths of the mine
to see if the drill will
break through somewhere there,
but they realize it is too dangerous
and head to back up.
Back on the surface,
after so many failures,
Sougarret has decided
on a risky new approach.
Instead of digging as fast as
they can to reach the workers,
they will now go painstakingly slow,
sacrificing speed for better accuracy.
It will take more days
to reach their target,
but if they keep missing,
it'll take even longer anyway.
The drills grind to half
of their original speed.
Days pass with this new slower approach,
and by August 22nd,
it has now been 17 days
since the collapse.
Many have privately given up hope,
but none dare to voice their thoughts
that it seems unlikely
they will find anyone alive at this point.
And then it happens again.
One of the drills reaches
an open cavern near the target area,
and, once again, the rescuers think
they hear tapping on the drill.
Not wanting to have a repeat of last time,
they brace themselves to
avoid getting their hopes up.
Once again, they send
the camera back down,
and this time something peculiar happens.
Once the drill reaches the surface,
someone points out that there is a small,
palm-sized red smudge on the drill.
Was that there earlier?
(suspenseful music)
Before they can investigate further,
someone else notices
that there is something
attached to the drill bit.
Tied to it, with rubber tubing,
there are pieces of paper.
There's no mistaking this.
Someone down below must
have attached this.
Carefully unwrapping the tubing,
rescuers begin to read
the three pieces of paper.
The first is a note that points out
where exactly the drill
has broken through.
The second is a personal
letter to a family member.
And the third is the one that
completely changes everything.
It says, "We are well
in The Refuge, the 33."
(people cheering)
Cheers ring out among the rescuers,
as 17 days after first hearing news
that their family members
were killed by an accident in the mine,
Maria Segovia and
everyone else in Camp Hope
hear the news that they have
been all found alive and well.
(people cheering)
- Euphoria in Chile as
33 miners are found alive
in a collapsed mine.
- It took 17 days to find the 33 miners.
- [Reporter] Trucks
carrying mining equipment
are cheered like heroes in a parade.
(upbeat music)
- [Narrator] But this is where
the real work just begins.
Now, that the workers have been found,
it's time to make first contact with them
and figure out how to
actually get them out.
A camera and a makeshift phone
is lowered down through the borehole,
and the President of
Chile, Sebastian Pinera,
is there to speak with Urzua
who confirms once more
that they are all alive and uninjured.
The most important first step
is to get the man stabilized.
Two additional boreholes are created
to serve as a lifeline
to the trapped workers.
The first initial hole is
used to send down supplies.
The second hole is used for communication.
And the third hole is
intended to be used for later
as a potential point of
rescue to get the men out.
And to the dismay of the miners,
the first shipment of supplies isn't food,
but rather bottles of glucose gel.
Since they haven't had a
proper meal in 18 days,
the miners can't jump
straight into real food,
or it'll make them sick.
They are happy to at least
receive fresh water though,
meaning they no longer need
to drink from the
industrial tank full of oil.
The 33 miners also receive
a shipment of medicine
containing vitamins and vaccinations.
Urzua decides to appoint
fellow miner, Yonni Barrios,
as their resident doctor in charge
of delivering the injections,
and Barrios will routinely
take man's vitals,
such as blood pressure,
in order to report back to the
medicine team above ground.
(intense music)
Meanwhile, Sougarret starts
coming up with a plan
for how to get them out of the mine.
All of the holes so far were narrow,
but now they would need to
drill a much wider hole,
which they estimate could
take up to four months,
time in which the giant diorite
block could move further
and potentially collapse the mine.
To speed the process up,
Sougarret decides to, once again,
employ multiple strategies at once,
and he comes up with three plans.
Plan A is use a drilling
rig that is used in mines
to create new shafts called a Strata 950.
It will first need to drill a pilot hole
to reach its target,
then drill the same
hole to widen it enough
that the man can be raised through.
Plan B is to use an air core drill
that typically drills wells
called a Shram 2130XD.
This one will use one of the
free boreholes already created
as its pilot hole and work to widen it,
first to 12 inches,
and then widen it once again to 28 inches.
Plan C is to use a
powerful oil drilling rig
called a RIG-421 that
won't need a pilot hole
and can theoretically
dig the required width
in just one single pass.
(intense music)
The entire operation would become known
as Operation San Lorenzo,
named after the patron saint of mining.
While all three drills are busy digging,
another team begins
working on the capsules
that the workers will need to enter
in order to be hoisted up to the surface.
To achieve this, officials from NASA
are called in to provide advice
to the Chilean Navy for
constructing the capsule.
And in total,
three of these Phoenix rescue
capsules are manufactured.
(intense music)
Meanwhile, Plan C is
running into an issue.
This is a drill that should be able
to create the rescue
hole in just one pass.
However, because of its massive size,
the angle it has to drill,
and because of the type of diorite rock
it must chew through,
it continuously wanders off target
and needs to be stopped and recalibrated,
significantly slowing its progress.
(intense music continues)
The next issue comes with Plan B.
Despite a strong start with
significant progress made,
reaching nearly half of the depth required
in its first widening pass,
the drill bit breaks
off into the borehole,
effectively blocking further progress
and making the hole useless.
And to make matters even worse,
Plan A runs into issues
with its hydraulics,
causing its drilling
to also come to a halt.
The sounds of the drill stopping
sends panic and anxiety
through the men trapped below,
as it becomes more realistic
that their rescue
really may not come for
several more months.
Most of the miners' hopes
were pinned on Plan B,
and so rather than
giving up on the borehole
and starting all over again,
the engineers came up
with a different idea.
They devise a special metal contraption
that is lowered into the hole
and is able to retrieve the broken bit.
And surprisingly, it works.
(intense music continues)
With the path cleared,
drilling for Plan B can resume,
news that come as a relief to everyone.
(reporter speaking non-English language)
- Today is the day.
As we speak, rescue teams
are continuing to test an empty capsule
to make sure that it's
safe enough for the miners
when they make the journey up.
- They'll be told to keep their hands in
and their faces back as that door closes.
(drill rattling)
- [Narrator] Finally, after 65 days
of being trapped underground,
what everyone has been so
eagerly waiting for happens.
The Plan B drill finishes
widening its borehole
enough that the team can lower
the Phoenix capsules through,
and the rescue operation
can enter its final phase.
First, a rescuer is lowered
down into the borehole
in order to assist the men from the bottom
with instructions on
how to enter the capsule
and make sure they are properly secured.
And when this rescuer reaches the bottom
and steps out of the capsule,
the 33 workers finally
get their first sight
of someone other than themselves,
someone from up above.
(intense music)
And now it's time to start
sending the men up one by one.
The order in which the men will go up
has already been determined.
And first up is the shift's
foreman, Florencio Avalos.
He and the three men who
will follow after him
are deemed the most fit.
And so if something goes wrong,
they will be most likely to be able
to extract themselves from the capsule
and make their way back down the borehole.
(intense music continues)
As Avalos begins his
ascent up towards freedom,
he begins to feel cool air
the closer he gets to the surface.
(intense music continues)
The entire journey takes about 15 minutes,
and as his head pokes above ground,
he catches a glimpse of a
crowd of people in hardhats
breaking out in cheers
of joy and celebration.
(intense music continues)
Up there, he is reunited with his family
and greeted by the rescue crew,
as well as by the Chilean President.
(intense music continues)
After Avalos is successfully extracted,
the next three fit workers are brought up,
followed by those deemed most at risk.
- [Reporter] Joy for the rescued miners
and pride for an entire country.
- [Reporter] It's the
greatest underground rescue
the world has ever seen.
- [Narrator] Each cycle
is faster than predicted,
and, though the rescue started at night,
as the morning sun begins to rise,
the remaining men are
instructed to wear sunglasses
in order to protect their
eyes from the harsh sunlight
after being underground
for over two months.
(intense music fades out)
Finally, it comes time for the
last worker to be raised up
to the surface, Shift Supervisor Urzua.
(intense music)
And cheers continue to ring
out as he takes his turn
to step outside of the capsule.
(crowd cheering and applauding)
Next, he declares to
President Pinera that,
as the boss, he's now
handing the shift over.
All that's left of the rescue now
is to bring up the rescuers
who were sent down to
aid in the operation,
and to send the miners
off to the hospital.
(siren wailing)
All things considered,
the workers are in great physical shape.
All but two of the workers are
released almost immediately,
with one man needing
further psychological tests
and the other requiring some dental work.
After only a few more days,
the last two men have
been released as well,
and all men are able to return home
where in most cases they
would find themselves
bombarded by journalists.
(suspenseful music)
- The rumors are proven to be true.
There has been an agreement
between the 33 miners
that there are some things that
could perhaps remain untold.
(suspenseful music continues)
- [Narrator] While they
were trapped in the mine,
the 33 had decided to make a pact.
Should they be rescued,
they will stand together as a unit
and only talk to one person
that they all agree upon
as to how they survived.
This way, no one man
would profit off the story
any more than the others.
However, because of this pact,
once the 33 were rescued,
the universal support for
the men trapped in the mine
began to crumble.
They did not speak with the journalists
that continuously showed up at their door,
and they refused to answer questions
about what exactly happened
in those 17 days before they were found.
Almost as if in retaliation,
the media began to fill in the gaps
with their own stories about the men,
and none were as apparent as the one
that spread like wildfire about the miner
who once acted as the resident
doctor, Yonni Barrios.
(somber music)
The story ran that he had cheated
and that his wife and
his secret girlfriend
first learned about
each other at Camp Hope
because of the accident.
In reality, Chile, with a
very Catholic population,
had only just legalized
divorce about five years prior.
And because of how new the
idea of divorce still was,
many couples still legally
remained married, just separated.
Barrios's wife and girlfriend
had known about each other
for long before the accident,
and Barrios himself mainly
lived with his girlfriend.
Yet, once journalists saw
that Barrios had a girlfriend
and a wife waiting for him in Camp Hope,
before looking any further
they published a story
of the two timing miner.
Many stories were also published
that painted the workers as freeloaders,
just looking for a get-rich-quick moment
because of their ordeal.
A wealthy businessman donated
5 million Chilean Pesos to each man,
equal to about 10,000 US Dollars.
And some of the men traveled the world
to appear on talk shows
and meet celebrities.
Stories were published
that the workers were racking
up gifts and expensive trips,
and yet in reality, any
actual help or compensation
for their ordeal was nowhere to be found,
not even within the legal system of Chile.
After a three year investigation,
no charges were ever
brought against the owners
of the San Jose mine.
(somber music continues)
The $10,000 they received dried up,
and they needed to get back to work
with some of the men
even choosing to go back to mining
because that is what they knew.
(intense music)
The story of the Chilean miners
is undoubtedly inspiring,
but it is also a story about
how media attention works.
If it weren't for Maria
Segovia creating noise,
the world might have
never noticed this story.
And as much as the world
cared about the men
when they were trapped down below,
once they were up,
the happy ending story was completed,
and these men were forgotten.
(intense music)
The Chilean miner rescue
is a powerful story
of human perseverance,
and perseverance can come in many forms.
Sometimes it can begin
with a simple choice,
the choice to risk everything
for a chance at something better,
such as in my video about the
incredible balloon escape.
(intense music continues)
Back when Germany was a divided country
with a brutal border strip
that made it impossible
to flee from the East German dictatorship,
two families came up with an insane idea.
They decided to build their
own homemade hot air balloon,
and they would risk their
lives to try to fly to freedom.
(intense music)
It is a thrilling story,
and I actually got to
interview Gunter Wetzel,
one of the men who built the balloon.
This documentary is part of
my Nebula original series
called "Under Exposure."
Apart from "The Balloon Escape,"
I also created a film about Flight MH17
that crashed over eastern Ukraine,
detailing how investigators were able
to trace back exactly
what led to the crash,
or my documentary about
the Bin Laden raid,
where I mapped out exactly
what happened when a US Seal team
stormed the compound
of the Al-Qaeda leader.
(intense music continues)
These are videos that are not made
for the YouTube algorithm,
but unrushed storytelling.
And all of them are available
right now on Nebula,
which is a streaming platform
that I'm building together
with other creators.
Since Nebula is a subscription service,
it allows us to have higher budgets
and create our dream projects.
And on top of these exclusive videos,
I also upload all my regular
YouTube videos early on Nebula,
so you can already watch
my next video today.
So go to nebula.tv/neo,
and make sure that you
use exactly this link
in order to get 40% off the annual plan.
All my exclusive videos are up there,
so thanks for the support,
and thank you so much
for watching this video.
(intense music continues)
(intense music fades out)